Guide to the Donald Oenslager Collection of Edward Gordon Craig
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Writings, 1906-1972; Series II; 1; (3 boxes)
  - WRITINGS OF OTHERS
    - Cheney, Sheldon
      - "Gordon Craig's Service to the Theatre," clipping of printed version, The Theatre Magazine, 1914
      - "Gordon Craig: The Theatre's Chief Revolutionary," clipping of printed version, Theatre Arts Monthly, 1927 Dec (Box 4, Folder 125)
    - Duncan, Isadora
      - My Life, typescript fragments, corrected, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 126)
    - Fletcher, Ifan Kyrle
      - "Edward Gordon Craig: A Check-List," printed version, annotated [by DO?], n.d. (Box 4, Folder 127)
    - Grossman, Harvey
      - "Gordon Craig and the Actor," carbon typescript, 1952 Apr 4 (Box 4, Folder 128)
    - Guidry, Lorelei
      - "Gordon Craig's Theatre Magazine: The Mask ," typescript thesis, 1963
        Includes: Letter to DO from Lorelei Guidry, 22 November 1963
    - Harrison, Austin
      - "Lady Diana Goes to the Ballet," typescript of an article published as "by the Editor" in The English Review, August 1911, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 133)
        With a holograph note by EGC, and an envelope addressed to F. A. King
    - Morris, Guido
      - "Chronology of the Work of Edward Gordon Craig," typescript and holograph, with annotations by EGC, 1946
    - Terry, Ellen
      - "Stage Decoration," clipping of printed version, The Windsor Magazine, [1906-07?] (Box 4, Folder 134)
    - Unidentified
      - "Craig and Oenslager in the 'New' Theatre," typescript (Box 4, Folder 135)
- Artwork and Theater Design, 1900-1972; Series III; 0.1; (.5 box)
  - EDWARD GORDON CRAIG
    - Artwork
      - Blank postcards of EGC woodcuts and stage design, from the Camden Arts Centre, centenary exhibition, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 136)
      - Bookplate design for Marion Morse MacKaye, reprinted on invitation to her memorial service, 1939 (Box 5, Folder 137)
      - "Christopher St. John," drawing [reproduction?], 1900
      - "The City," etching, used in A Portfolio of Etchings, 2 prints, [1907?] (Box 5, Folder 138)
      - Clippings and photocopies of artwork (Box 5, Folder 139-140)
      - "Ellen Terry as 'Ophelia', " black and white lithograph[?] (Box 5, Folder 141)
      - Forest scene[?], woodcut, 4 prints, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 142)
        "Printed only for subscribers to The Mask "
      - Man near a windmill, woodcut used in The Page (Box 5, Folder 143)
        Mounted on part of an envelope addressed to George Plank
      - Page of EGC's stationary, with woodcut design, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 144)
      - A Portfolio of Etchings, limited edition of 12 etchings in a cloth box, 1907
        Includes: Prospectus describing the portfolio, and a poetic essay entitled "Motion," signed "to GWP"
      - A Second Portfolio of Etchings, limited edition of 12 etchings in a cloth box, [1907?]
        Includes: Prospectus describing the portfolio
      - Postcard with reproduction of a lithograph for an 1899 cover of The Dome, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 145)
      - Wood block of the alphabet, 1900 (Box 5, Folder 146)
        Includes: Letter to DO from Arnold Rood, 21 May 1971, and photocopy of letter from Janet Leeper to Rood, 28 November 1967
      - Woodcut of a man, numbered "33", n.d.
      - Woodcut of Hecuba, numbered "72", n.d.
      - Unidentified woman, lithograph[?], n.d. (Box 5, Folder 147)
    - Theater Design
      - "Design for a Scene in 'Dido and Aeneas'," color print of a woodcut (Box 5, Folder 148)
      - Model screen made for EGC's experimental theater, wood and paper (Box 5, Folder 149)
        Inscribed to Ewald Junge from EGC
      - Photocopy of patent application for folding screens, 1910 Jan 24 (Box 5, Folder 150)
        Includes: Photocopy of a 1911 photograph of the screens
      - Photograph of a model for the stage design for Macbeth, Act I, Scene I, 1909 (Box 5, Folder 151)
      - Photograph of a model for the stage design for Macbeth, Act II, 1909 (Box 5, Folder 152)
      - Stage design for an unidentified production, n.d.
  - ARTWORK BY OTHERS
    - Goya, Francisco. Prints of two etchings from The Disasters of War: "Gatesca pantomima" [Cat's Pantomime] and "Esta no lo es menos" [No Less Curious] (Box 5, Folder 153)
    - Marks, Claude. Reproduction of drawing of EGC on an exhibition flyer, 1961 (Box 5, Folder 154)
    - Rothenstein, William. Photograph of a drawing of EGC from 1911, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 155)
    - Empty folder (Box 5, Folder 156)
    - Smith, Pamela Colman. Hand colored lithograph of Ellen Terry in costume, 1903
    - Unidentified. Photograph of a drawing of EGC, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 157)
    - Unidentified. Sketch of waiters, pen, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 158)
- Photographs, 1888-1960; Series IV; 0.1; (.5 box)
  - PHOTOGRAPHS OF EDWARD GORDON CRAIG
    - Photos by David Lees, taken in Vence (France)
      - In bed, 1951 (Box 5, Folder 159)
      - In straw hat, 5 photographs, 1949-51 (Box 5, Folder 160)
      - Looking over city, 1951 (Box 5, Folder 161)
      - Seated, 1951 (Box 5, Folder 162)
      - Seated, outdoors, 1951 (Box 5, Folder 163)
      - Smoking, 1951
      - With back turned, 1951 (Box 5, Folder 164)
      - With cigarette, 1949
      - With David Lees, 1949 (Box 5, Folder 165)
      - With pipe, n.d.
    - Other Photographs of Craig
      - "Craig mas André Corniche du Malran[?]," 3 color prints (Box 5, Folder 166)
      - "Gordon Craig and Gertrude Robins at Arena Goldoni [Florence]," photograph by Charles E. Dawson (Box 5, Folder 167)
      - In hat and cape, color print, 1960 (Box 5, Folder 168)
      - Photograph by Arnold Rood, Vence (France), 1960 (Box 5, Folder 169)
      - Photograph by James H. Butler, Vence (France), 1957 (Box 5, Folder 170)
      - Portrait, ca. 1888 (Box 5, Folder 171)
      - Portrait, 1890 (Box 5, Folder 172)
      - Smoking, in Tourette-sur-Loup (France), photograph by Arnold Rood, 1960 Jun (Box 5, Folder 173)
      - With James H. Butler, Vence (France), 2 photos, 1957 (Box 5, Folder 174)
      - With unidentified woman, in Tourette- sur-Loup (France), photograph by Arnold Rood, 1960 (Box 5, Folder 175)
  - OTHER PHOTOGRAPHS
    - Terry, Ellen, 1910 (Box 5, Folder 176)
    - "The Terry Family, photo by Lewis Carroll ... Benjamin, Florence, Ellen, Kate, Fred, Marion, Sarah", n.d. (Box 5, Folder 177)
    - Unidentified exhibition of Craig items, 4 photographs, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 178)
- Subject Files, 1881-1972; Series V; 0.8; (2 boxes)
  - CLIPPINGS
    - About Edward Gordon Craig
      - Articles, 1905-72, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 179-181)
      - Drawings and caricatures, 1922-28, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 182)
      - Interviews, 1907-57, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 183)
      - The Mask, 1912, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 184)
      - News stories, 1920-64, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 185)
      - Obituaries, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 186)
      - "Proposed alliance" with Charles Blake Cochran, 1930, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 187)
      - Photographs, 1890-1949, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 188)
      - Reviews of exhibitions, 1911-49, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 189)
      - Reviews of theater productions, 1928, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 190)
      - School for the Art of the Theatre, 1912-15, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 191)
      - Other clippings about EGC, 1911-68, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 192)
    - Other Clippings
      - Isadora Duncan theater, 1912, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 193)
      - Theater design, 1912-30, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 194)
      - Other clippings, 1919-66, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 195)
  - EXHIBITIONS
    - "Architects in the Theatre, 1500-1800"
      - Description and list of books included in the exhibition, with an article by A. M. (Alois Maria) Nagler, 1969 Feb (Box 6, Folder 196)
        In: Gazette of the Grolier Club
      - Photocopy of a description of the exhibition, with corrections, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 197)
        Includes: ALS to DO from Robert Nikirk
      - Exhibition labels, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 198-200)
    - Other Exhibitions
      - Exhibition catalogs, 1901-72, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 201-203)
      - Exhibition posters and flyers, 1913-71 (Box 6, Folder 204)
  - THE MASK
    - Advertising brochures, 1912-23, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 205)
    - Blank postcards advertising The Mask, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 206)
    - Holograph list of issues, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 207)
    - List of pseudonyms used by EGC in The Mask, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 208)
      Includes: Letters to DO from Lorelei Guidry, 30 December 1962
    - The Marionette, advertising leaflet, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 209)
    - Photocopy of an inscription by EGC in a 1913 copy of The Mask given to Betty Lou Holland, listing several of his pseudonyms, 1959 (Box 6, Folder 210)
      Includes: Letter to DO from Robert M. MacGregor, 16 February 1960
    - Poster advertisement, n.d.
    - Printed cards accompanying complementary review copies, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 211)
    - "Supplement to The Mask July 1910: Mr. Frohman's Fine Proposal," printed version (Box 6, Folder 212)
    - Other papers, 1914, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 213)
  - THE PAGE
    - Advertising brochures, 1899, 1901 (Box 6, Folder 214)
    - Order forms, 1898 (Box 6, Folder 215)
  - THEATER PROGRAMS
    - Productions with Edward Gordon Craig as an Actor
      - Lyceum Theatre (London, England)
        - Plays by William Shakespeare
          - Cymbeline, 1896 (Box 7, Folder 216)
          - King Henry the Eighth, 1892 (Box 7, Folder 217)
          - King Lear, 1893 (Box 7, Folder 218)
          - King Richard III, 1897 (Box 7, Folder 219)
        - Plays by Others
          - Becket, by Alfred, Lord Tennyson, 1893 (Box 7, Folder 220)
          - The Corsican Brothers, by Alexandre Dumas and Nance Oldfield, by Charles Reade, 1891 (Box 7, Folder 221)
          - The Dead Heart, by Watts Phillips, revised by Walter Herries Pollock, 1889 (Box 7, Folder 222)
          - Olivia, by W. G. (William Gorman) Wills, 1891 (Box 7, Folder 223)
          - Ravenswood, by Herman Charles Merivale, [1891] (Box 7, Folder 224)
      - Plays Produced in Other Theaters
        - Eugene Aram, by W. G. (William Gorman) Wills, Lyceum Company, Star Theatre (New York, N.Y.), 1885 (Box 7, Folder 225)
        - Macbeth, by William Shakespeare, Miss Sarah Thorne's Company, Opera House, Chatham (England), 1896 (Box 7, Folder 226)
    - Productions Directed or Designed by Edward Gordon Craig
      - Plays by William Shakespeare
        - Macbeth, The American Theatre, 2 different programs, 1928-29 (Box 7, Folder 227)
          Includes: Letter to DO from Frank C. P. McGlinn, 11 August 1969
        - Macbeth, Broad St. Theatre, 1928 (Box 7, Folder 228)
          In: Plays and Players
        - Macbeth, Knickerbocker Theatre, 1928 (Box 7, Folder 229)
        - Much Ado About Nothing, The Imperial Theatre, [1903] (Box 7, Folder 230)
      - Plays by Others
        - For Sword or for Song, by Robert George Legge, Louise Calvert and Raymond Rôze, Shaftesbury Theatre (England), 1903 (Box 7, Folder 231)
        - The Vikings, by Henrik Ibsen, The Imperial Theatre, 1903 (Box 7, Folder 232)
    - Productions with "Archaeology" E. W. (Edward William) Godwin
      - Envelope with holograph notes explaining EWG's involvement in the productions, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 233)
      - Claudian, by Henry Herman and W. G. (William Gorman) Wills, Princess's Theatre (London, England), 1883 (Box 7, Folder 234)
      - Clito, by Sydney Grundy and Wilson Barrett, Princess's Theatre (London, England), [1886] (Box 7, Folder 235)
      - The Cup, by Alfred, Lord Tennyson and The Corsican Brothers, by Alexandre Dumas, Lyceum Theatre, 1881 (Box 7, Folder 236)
      - Hamlet, by William Shakespeare, Princess's Theatre (London, England), [1884] (Box 7, Folder 237)
    - Other Programs
      - "A Matinee in Aid of the Ellen Terry Memorial," The Palace Theatre, 1929 (Box 7, Folder 237a)
        Includes: Prints of woodcuts by EGC
  - OTHER FILES
    - Bibliography of publications in which EGC is mentioned, printed version, 1931 (Box 7, Folder 238)
      Pages taken from a copy of Gordon Craig and the Theatre, by Enid Rose
    - Blank postcards of Venice and Tourette- sur-Loup (France) (Box 7, Folder 239)
    - Book prospectuses, 1902-57, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 240)
      Includes: ALS from Ewald Junge [to DO?], 16 June 1961
    - British Theatre Conference. Agenda for the opening plenary session, printed version with annotations, 1948 (Box 7, Folder 241)
    - Chapter One, printed periodical, issue on EGC, 1962
      Includes: Note to DO from Herman Rosse
    - "God Save the King!" printed letter by EGC and Guido Morris, 1911
      Includes: Receipt from the Beauchamp Bookshop Ltd. to DO, 1 February 1960
    - Lists of books written or illustrated by EGC, books about EGC, and exhibitions of his works, carbon typescripts, 1957, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 242)
    - Marbled end paper[?]
    - Notes and other papers regarding the proposed Isadora Duncan theater, [ca. 1912?] (Box 7, Folder 243)
    - "Notes on Mr. Gordon Craig's Personal Collection at St. Germain," carbon typescript, 1940 Jan (Box 7, Folder 244)
      Includes: 2 clippings about the sale of EGC's papers to the Bibliothèque de l'Arsenal
    - Outline for a speech at EGC's induction as an honorary member of the United Scenic Artists, 1961 (Box 7, Folder 245)
      Includes: Clipping about the event
    - Page from a sales catalog of EGC materials, 1960 Sep (Box 7, Folder 246)
    - "A Partially Accurate Transcript of the Proceedings of the United Scenic Artists Tribute to Edward Gordon Craig", 1961 Jan (Box 7, Folder 247)
      Includes: Transcripts of speeches by Edward Craig, Laurence Irving, Howard Bay and Sir John Gielgud, a photocopy of a letter to EGC from S. N. Behrman, photocopies of letters to John V. King from Val Henry Gielgud, John Rothenstein, Eric Bentley and a Lady- in-Waiting to Queen Elizabeth, and a photocopy of a telegram to King from Peter Brook
    - Printed invitations to a dinner honoring EGC, 1911 Jun (Box 7, Folder 248)
    - Printed invitations to birthday parties for EGC held by Arnold Rood, 1960-64 (Box 7, Folder 249)
    - The Questors Limited. Brochure for the "New Theatre", n.d. (Box 7, Folder 250)
    - Sales catalogs of artwork and designs by EGC, 1902-38, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 251)
    - Sample papers "for covers of the Goldoni books", [ca. 1905] (Box 7, Folder 252)
    - Other papers, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 253)
- Oversize, 6.25; (4 boxes)
  - "Gordon Craig's Service to the Theatre," clipping of printed version (in Series II), 1914 (Box 8, Folder 254)
  - "Chronology of the Work of Edward Gordon Craig," typescript and holograph (in Series II), 1946 (Box 8, Folder 255)
  - "Christopher St. John," drawing [reproduction?] (in Series III), 1900 (Box 8, Folder 256)
  - Clippings and photocopies of artwork (in Series III) (Box 8, Folder 257)
  - Woodcut of a man, numbered "33" (in Series III), n.d. (Box 8, Folder 258)
  - Woodcut of Hecuba, numbered "72" (in Series III), n.d. (Box 8, Folder 259)
  - Stage design for an unidentified production (in Series III), n.d. (Box 8, Folder 259a)
  - Smith, Pamela Colman. Hand colored lithograph of Ellen Terry in costume (in Series III), 1903 (Box 8, Folder 259b)
  - Photograph of EGC smoking (in Series IV) (Box 8, Folder 260)
  - Photograph of EGC with cigarette (in Series IV), 1949 (Box 8, Folder 261)
  - Photograph of EGC with pipe (in Series IV) (Box 8, Folder 262)
  - Exhibition posters and flyers (in Series V), 1913-71 (Box 8, Folder 263)
  - Order forms for The Page (in Series V) (Box 8, Folder 264)
  - Chapter One, printed periodical, issue on EGC (in Series V), 1962 (Box 8, Folder 265)
  - "God Save the King!" printed letter by EGC and Guido Morris (in Series V), 1911 (Box 8, Folder 266)
  - Scrapbook with printed pages of the libretto and music of the Ring (in Series II) (Box 9, Folder 267)
  - A Portfolio of Etchings (in Series III), 1907 (Box 10, Folder 268)
  - A Second Portfolio of Etchings (in Series III), [1907?] (Box 11, Folder 269)
  - Marbled end paper[?] (in Series V) (Box bsd, folder 270)
  - Poster advertisement for The Mask (in Series V), n.d. (Box bsd, folder 271)
- Restricted Fragile, 0.8; (3 boxes)
  Restricted Fragile materials may only be consulted with permission of the appropriate curator. Preservation photocopies or photographic prints for reference use have been substituted in the main files
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  - Box 1, folder 33 (Box 12, Folder 272)
  - Box 1, folder 34 (Box 12, Folder 273)
  - Box 1, folder 35 (Box 12, Folder 274)
  - Box 1, folder 39 (Box 12, Folder 275)
  - Box 1, folder 41 (Box 12, Folder 276)
  - Box 1, folder 42 (Box 12, Folder 277)
  - Box 2, folder 54 (Box 12, Folder 278)
  - Box 2, folder 55 (Box 12, Folder 279)
  - Box 2, folder 57 (Box 12, Folder 280)
  - Box 2, folder 58 (Box 12, Folder 281)
  - Box 2, folder 61 (Box 12, Folder 282)
  - Box 2, folder 62 (Box 12, Folder 283)
  - Box 2, folder 63 (Box 12, Folder 284)
  - Box 2, folder 64 (Box 12, Folder 285)
  - Box 2, folder 65 (Box 12, Folder 286)
  - Box 2, folder 66 (Box 12, Folder 287)
  - Box 2, folder 67 (Box 12, Folder 288)
  - Box 2, folder 69 (Box 12, Folder 289)
  - Box 2, folder 70 (Box 12, Folder 290)
  - Box 2, folder 71 (Box 12, Folder 291)
  - Box 2, folder 72 (Box 12, Folder 292)
  - Box 2, folder 73 (Box 12, Folder 293)
  - Box 2, folder 74 (Box 12, Folder 294)
  - Box 2, folder 76 (Box 12, Folder 295)
  - Box 2, folder 81 (Box 12, Folder 296)
  - Box 2, folder 82 (Box 12, Folder 297)
  - Box 2, folder 83 (Box 12, Folder 298)
  - Box 2, folder 95 (Box 12, Folder 299)
  - Box 2, folder 96 (Box 12, Folder 300)
  - Box 2, folder 97 (Box 12, Folder 301)
  - Box 2, folder 98 (Box 12, Folder 302)
  - Box 3, folder 99 (Box 12, Folder 303)
  - Box 3, folder 116 (Box 12, Folder 304)
  - Box 3, folder 119 (Box 12, Folder 305)
  - Box 5, folder 139 (Box 12, Folder 306)
  - Box 6, folders 179-180 (Box 12, Folder 307)
  - Box 6, folder 182 (Box 12, Folder 308)
  - Box 6, folder 183 (Box 12, Folder 309)
  - Box 6, folder 184 (Box 12, Folder 310)
  - Box 6, folder 185 (Box 12, Folder 311)
  - Box 6, folder 186 (Box 12, Folder 312)
  - Box 6, folder 187 (Box 12, Folder 313)
  - Box 6, folder 188 (Box 12, Folder 314)
  - Box 6, folder 189 (Box 12, Folder 315)
  - Box 6, folder 190 (Box 12, Folder 316)
  - Box 6, folder 191 (Box 12, Folder 317)
  - Box 6, folder 192 (Box 12, Folder 318)
  - Box 6, folder 193 (Box 12, Folder 319)
  - Box 6, folder 194 (Box 12, Folder 320)
  - Box 6, folder 195 (Box 12, Folder 321)
  - Box 7, folder 247 (Box 12, Folder 322)
  - Box 5, folder 146 (Box 13, Folder 323)
  - Box 5, folder 149 (Box 14, Folder 324)